Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - [Tophet], Such Tophet was; so looked the grinning fiend; 1769 (pr. 1783); poems.tapr
    - [untitled], 1769; mss.0165; poems.tapr; 1 transcript in the hand of Michael Tyson c. 245 mm x 180 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 138, 92
      Copy of Tyson's etching with the text, annotated "Gray". Above the sketch is an annotation by William Cole "Mr. Etough of Therfeild in Hartfordshire, obiit 1757", and on verso "Given to me by Mr. Tyson in Nov: 1769. Wm. Cole". Bound in a volume entitled History of King's College Cambridge, vol. IV, XVI, bequeathed by Rev. W. Cole.
    - Lines by ... on Mr. E___'s characature, [between 1793 and c. 1800]; mss.0247; poems.tapr; [1?] transcript 240 mm x 180 mm (volume); FOLG
      Microfilm copy available in Microfilm Collection, FILM Fo. 2321, Microfilm of M.a.182, 1 microfilm reel: negative, 12:1, 12 feet; 35 mm.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36726>
      Transcript, here beginning "Such E___ was, so grinn'd the brawling fiend", in a volume entitled Manuscript Collection, a miscellaneous collection in prose and verse in which are included several original pieces 1793 ... Vol. I (97 leaves), compiled by A. S. W.
    - [untitled], [undated]; mss.0251; poems.tapr; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand (6 lines) c. 55 mm x 160 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=111908>
      Transcript (6 lines) in an unidentified hand, here beginning "Such Tophet was, so grinned the bawling fiend" and attributed above "By Mr Gray", in a quarto volume of miscellaneous pieces of poetry, entitled Miscellaneous Poetry and "presented by Rev. T. Crompton", written in the 18th and 19th centuries, to which the names of the respective authors are assigned.
  - [Translation from Dante, Inferno Canto xxxiii 1-78], From his dire food the grisly felon raised; 1849 and 1884; poems.tdin
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 61-63
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 23-25
    Written probably in 1737 or 1738 when Gray was translating other Italian verse by Tasso and Petrarch. First published, 15 lines only, in The Gentleman's Magazine N.S. 32 (October 1849), 343, published in full in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. I, 157-160
    , as Dante. Canto 33, dell' Inferno.
    - Dante, Canto 33 dell' Inferno, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0167; poems.tdin; 4 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 139, 92-93
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, introduced "DANTE. It is uncertain when Mr Gray translated the following Story from Dante; but most probably very early, and when he was making himself Master of the Italian language.", headed Dante, Canto 33 dell' Inferno, and annotated "N.B. The above is not in Grays Writing, but in a clear large hand. perhaps Mr. Stonehewer's. (yes.)", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 70-73.
    - Translation in blank verse of Dante's Ugolino c. xxxiii., [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0168; poems.tdin; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 1-4, 82-84] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 140, 93
      Transcript of ll. 1-4 and 82-4 in the hand of John Mitford, here beginning "From his dire food the greisly father raisd", annotated "Mason says, Gray translated this when learning Italian" and "N.B. The MS is not in Gray's writing", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 182-183.
    - Translation in Blank Verse of Dante's Ugolino c. xxxiii., [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0166; poems.tdin; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 1-4, 82-84] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of ll. 1-4 and 82-84 in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), annotated "Mason says Gray translated this, when learning Italian", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 29.
  - [Translation from Statius, Thebaid VI 646-88, 704-24], Then thus the king: 'Whoe'er the quoit can wield; 1853; poems.tra6
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 54-55
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 17-19
    Written before the end of May 1736 when Gray was learning Italian, and sent in two letters, dated [8 May 1736] (ll. 646-88) and [before 24 May 1736] (ll. 704-24), to Richard West. Gray's translation of ll. 689-703 has not survived. Translation of ll. 646-88 (59 lines) first published, untitled, in
    Mitford (ed.), Correspondence of Gray and Mason (1853), letter I, 2-4
    , and of ll. 704-24 (27 lines) first published in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), section I, 9-10.
    - E lib: 6to Thebaidos, 8 May [1736]; mss.0174; poems.tra6; [?] autograph fair copy; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 145, 93
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 22, vol. i, 38-41 (subscription required)
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 614(?), 10, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 244, 74
      Autograph fair copy of a translation of Thebaid, VI, 646-88, headed E lib: 6to Thebaidos, in a letter to Richard West, 8 May [1736].
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0213; poems.tra6; 3 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 32-52, 1-31, 53-59] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Transcript, here untitled, of ll. 32-52, 1-31, 53-59, in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 192r, 193r, 194r.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0173; poems.tra6; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 1-2, 51-52] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 93
      Transcript of ll. 1-2 and 51-52 in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 69.
  - [Translation from Statius, Thebaid IX 319-26], Crenaeus, whom the nymph Ismenis bore; 1915; poems.tra9
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 57-58
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 277
    Written probably as a school exercise at Eton between 1725 and 1734, possibly Gray's earliest composition in English. First published in
    Toynbee (ed.), Correspondence (1915), vol. ii, 299-300
    with a facsimile.
    - [untitled], [between 1725 and 1734]; mss.0169; poems.tra9; 1 autograph draft, partial [ll. 1-13]; PBCC
      . Facsimile in
      Toynbee (ed.), Correspondence (1915), vol. ii, following p. 298
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 141, 93
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 57n
      Autograph draft of ll. 1-13, here untitled, together with MS 0170.
    - [untitled], [between 1725 and 1734]; mss.0170; poems.tra9; 1 autograph fair copy, ll. 14-16 revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 142, 93
      Autograph (ll. 1-13 fair copy, ll. 14-16 revised), here untitled, including a transcript of the Latin original between ll. 13 and 14, annotated in the hand of Horace Walpole "This written when he was very young", together with MS 0169.
  - [Translation] From Tasso [Gerusalemme Liberata] Canto 14, Stanza 32-9., Dismissed at length, they break through all delay; 1814; poems.trgl
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 58-60
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 21-23
    Written in 1737 when Gray was translating other Italian verse by Dante and Petrarch and sent in a letter to Richard West, [22 May 1737]. First published in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 90-92
    - From Tasso. Canto, 14, Stanza, 32, 1738; mss.0171; poems.trgl; 2 autograph fair copy, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 143, 93
      Autograph fair copy, revised, translation from Gerusalemme Liberata, headed From Tasso. Canto, 14, Stanza, 32 in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 95-96.
    - [untitled], [22 May 1737]; mss.0172; poems.trgl; [?] autograph; YALE
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 144, 93
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 37*, vol. iii, 1315-1319
      Autograph, here untitled, in a letter to Richard West, [22 May 1737].
  - [Translation of Ode 'Away; let nought to love displeasing'], Vah, tenero quodcunque potest obsistere amori; 1890; poems.lt24
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 115-117, 250-251 (with English prose translation and the original English version)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 287-290 (with English prose translation and the original English version)
    Written probably as a school exercise at Eton between 1725 and 1734. First published, untitled, in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 298-300
    - [untitled], [between 1725 and 1734]; mss.0175; poems.lt24; [?] autograph; [privately owned]
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 146, 93
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (29 February 1960), lot 67
      Autograph in pencil and inked over, here untitled, bound into a copy of James Boswell, Life of Samuel Johnson (London, 1791), owned (1966) by Charles W. Traylen Booksellers (out of business since 2003 ).
      MS 0176.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0176; poems.lt24; 2 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 147, 93
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 250
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, untitled, but identified "N.B. The above is a free Translation of Gilb. Coopers Ode / Away let Nought to Love displeasing / ..." and annotated "The following Poem is written with Ink by Mason over Gray's Pencil, which was very faint, in order apparently to preserve it." and "N.B. Grays writing perceptible below the Ink-letters", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 86-87.
      MS 0176 apparently transcribed from MS 0175.
    - Poem, [between c. 1750 and c. 1775]; mss.0246; poems.lt24; 2 transcript; FOLG
      Microfilm copy available in Microfilm Collection, FILM Fo. 107a, Microfilm of Y.d.183 (1-14), 1 microfilm reel: negative, 16:1, 7 feet; 35 mm.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=56598> (no author attribution)
      Poem in English, beginning "Away! let nought to love displeasing", and Latin verse translation beginning "Vah! tenero quodcunque potest obsistere amori", from the G. E. Solly and Mrs. M. A. Carew sale of Garrick MSS at Sotheby's, June 18-21, 1928.
  - [Translations from the Greek Anthology], Fertur Aristophanis fatorum arcana rogatum, [etc.]; 1814 and 1890; poems.lt25
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 170-178 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 332-337 (with English prose translation)
    Thirteen small pieces, subsumed under the work title [Translations from the Greek Anthology], presumably written late in Gray's Latin period, after his return from the Continent in 1742. First published in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 94-97
    , except nos. [I] and [XII], first published in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 295
    . No. [VI] was first published as Nymph offering a Statue of herself to Venus and beginning "Te tibi, sancta, fero nudam; formosias, ipsa". First published complete and in Gray's order in
    Bradshaw (ed.), Poetical Works (1891), 168-172
    - [I] From the Greek, [after 1742]; mss.0177; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 149, 94
      Autograph fair copy in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 287.
    - [II] From the Greek of Antiphilus Byzantius In Medeae Imaginem, Nobile Timomachi Opus, [after 1742]; mss.0178; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 150, 94
    - [III] Imitation of the Greek; of Paul Silentiarius. In Bacchae Furentis Statuam, [after 1742]; mss.0179; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 151, 94
    - [IV] From the Greek, of Posidippus. In Alexandrum, AEre Effictum, [after 1742]; mss.0180; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 152, 94
    - [V] From the Greek. [Anonymous.] In Niobes Statuam, [after 1742]; mss.0181; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 153, 94
    - [VI] From the Greek, of Lucian, offering a Statue of herself to Venus, [after 1742]; mss.0182; poems.lt25; 1 autograph, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 154, 94
      Autograph, revised, the first line altered from "Te tibi, sancta, fero nudam: formosius ipsâ" in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 287.
    - [VII] From the Greek of Statyllius Flaccus. In Amorem dormientem, [after 1742]; mss.0183; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 155, 94
    - [VIII] From a Fragment of Plato, [after 1742]; mss.0184; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 156, 94
      Autograph fair copy in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 288.
    - [IX] From the Greek of Marianus. In Fontem aquae calidae, [after 1742]; mss.0185; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 157, 95
    - [X] From Lucillius, [after 1742]; mss.0186; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 158, 95
    - [XI] Imitated from the Greek of Posidippus. Ad Amorem, [after 1742]; mss.0187; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 159, 95
    - [XII].... of Bassus, [after 1742]; mss.0188; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 160, 95
      Autograph fair copy, headed "...Of Bassus", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 288.
    - [XIII].... of Rufinus, [after 1742]; mss.0189; poems.lt25; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 161, 95
      Autograph fair copy, headed "Of Rufinus...", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 288.
  - The Triumphs of Owen. A Fragment, Owen's praise demands my song; 1768; poems.trow
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 35-36
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 228-233
    Written probably in 1760 or 1761 when Gray was living in London. Based on a Latin translation by Evan Evans of the original Welsh Arwyain Owain Gwynnedd by Gwalchmai ap Meilyr. First published in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - The Triumphs of Owen, a Fragment from the Welch, [1760 or 1761]; mss.0190; poems.trow; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 162, 95
      Autograph fair copy, with four lines at the end intended to follow l. 26, here entitled The Triumphs of Owen, a Fragment from the Welch, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1068.
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0191; poems.trow; 2 autograph fair copy 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 163, 95
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=137227>
      Autograph fair copy, untitled but numbered 9. and identified on f. 3r as "9. The Triumphs of Owen, a fragment", headed "Prefix...Owen succeeded his Father Griffin in the principality of North-Wales, A:D: 1120. this battle was fought near forty years afterwards. (from Mr Evans's Specimens of the Welch poetry. Lond: 1764. 4to)", including an explanatory note of "The Dragon-Son", used as printer's copy for Poems ( 1768 ), in MS instructions to Dodsley, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0192; poems.trow; [2?] autograph 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 164, 95
      Autograph, untitled but numbered 9. and identified from the table of contents as "9. The Triumphs of Owen (from the Welch)", and headed "Note) Owen succeeded his Father Griffin in the principality of North Wales, A:D: 1120. this battle was fought near 40 years afterwards, (from Mr Evans's Specimens of the Welch poetry. Lond: 1764.4to)" together with a note on the Dragon-Son, in MS Instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - The Triumphs of Owen. A Fragment. From Mr. Evans's specimens of Welch Poetry; London, 1764, Quarto, 1780[?]; mss.0225; poems.trow; 6 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Triumphs of Owen. A Fragment (p. 93) (Ode X. [p. 95]). The poem, which includes Gray's notes and the additional lines after l. 26 by Mason, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - The triumphs of Owen Gwynedd a fragment, [after 1773]; mss.0274; poems.trow; [?] transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston 190mm x 120mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 624, item O1156
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10633>
      Transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston, entitled The triumphs of Owen Gwynedd a fragment, in his autograph Select, and Miscellaneous Poems, Scraps, Mottos &c, 1773 and later, a Commonplace book of verse by Dovaston and others.
  - [Verse Fragments], Gratitude; 1890; poems.vsfr
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 196
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 277-278
    Written probably in 1754, copied by William Mason from Gray's pocketbook for that year. First published, among "Thoughts and Verse Fragments", in
    Tovey (ed.), Gray and his Friends (1890), 269-270
    - [untitled], [1754]; mss.0193; poems.vsfr; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 165, 95
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, 12 lines beginning "Gratitude/ The Joy that trembles in her eye", within the "Extract from Mr Gray's Pocket Books... 1754", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1110.
  - William Shakespeare to Mrs Anne, Regular Servant to the Revd Mr Precentor of York, A moment's patience, gentle Mistress Anne!; 1853; poems.wsma
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 80-81
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 252-255
    Written early in July 1765 while on a visit to Thomas Wharton at Old Park, Durham, and sent in a letter to William Mason, [c. 8 July 1765]. First published in
    Mitford (ed.), Correspondence of Gray and Mason (1853), letter XC, 339-340
    - William Shakespeare To Mrs Anne, Regular Servant to the Revd Mr Precentor of York, [8 July 1765?]; mss.0195; poems.wsma; 1 autograph; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 166, 96
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 407, vol. ii, 879-881 (subscription required)
      Autograph in a letter to William Mason, [c. 8 July 1765].
    - [untitled], [1765]; mss.0196; poems.wsma; 1 autograph draft, the whole erased; [privately owned]
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 167, 96, in a notebook, item GrT 295, 109
      Toynbee, "Newly Discovered Draft" (1930), MS transcribed and discussed
      Autograph draft, here untitled and the whole erased, owned (1988) by Lt.-Col. John Murray.
    - Verses from Wm Shakspeare to Mrs Anne Regular Servant to the Revd Mr Precentor of York, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0197; poems.wsma; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 168, 96
      Transcript, with stanza 5 following stanza 2, in the hand of John Mitford, here entitled Verses from Wm Shakspeare to Mrs Anne Regular Servant to the Revd Mr Precentor of York and annotated "Tell me, if you don't like this, and I'll send you a worse", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 185.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0194; poems.wsma; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 95
      Transcript, with stanza 5 following stanza 2, here untitled and annotated "Tell me if you don't like this, & I will send you a worse", in the hand of John Mitford (crossed out), in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 31v.